Guide to the William Ryder Mathers Collection of David Wojnarowicz and Montanna MSS.433
Fales Library and Special Collections
William Ryder Mathers Collection of David Wojnarowicz and Montanna
1982-1990
Fales Library and Special Collections
Houston, M. (Montanna)
MSS.433
1.75 Linear Feet in 1 manuscript box, 1 half manuscript box, and 1 oversize flat box.
Montanna Houston was a writer, artist and musician who lived in New York City and later in Houston, Texas. This collection includes correspondence, collages and twelve-step program narratives written by Houston. The correspondence is mostly addressed to William Mathers, and there is one letter from Wojnarowicz to Montanna.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged alphabetically, except for the single oversize folder listed at the end.
Related Materials
The David Wojnarowicz Papers, MSS 092
Nancy Woolley/Montanna Houston Correspondence, MSS 436
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Biographical Note
Born Monte Hewson (circa 1952-1990), Montanna Houston (which he also stylized as Montana, Montini, and Montanna Hewston) was an artist, musician, writer, and contemporary of David Wojnarowicz, Richard Kern and Tommy Turner. Houston was raised by an adoptive family, whom he referred to as his step-family, and spent his childhood in Texas. After moving to New York in his mid-twenties, he met and became friends with Kern and Turner around 1979, and later met Wojnarowicz through the two filmmakers. Houston acted in Kern's Stray Dogs (1985) as well as Where Evil Dwells (1985), an unfinished Turner and Wojnarowicz film, in which he was cast as Satan (Joe Coleman is also credited as this character). He also contributed to many of Turner and Kern's zines. For most of his adult life, Houston lived with mental health issues and severe substance use. He left New York in 1986 to return to Houston, Texas, where his adoptive family still lived, and checked himself into West Oak Hospital for treatment. The twelve-step program he took part in there was an important part to his recovery from addiction. Houston died by suicide in 1990.
Scope and Contents
This small collection is made up mostly of correspondence from Montanna to his friend William Mathers, who was living in Dallas at the time these letters were written. Much of the material is undated, but most of it seems to have been written in 1989. Along with the letters, he often sent collages made up of newspaper and magazine clippings, some of which are pasted onto "pediatrics therapy record" stationary, as well as found objects. Over the course of the correspondence, he refers to Mathers with a series of nicknames derived affectionately from "worm," including "Wormus," "Verm," and "Wormicus." Houston also sent Mathers sheet music he had written, as well as addiction narratives from his twelve-step program, and an invitation to attend a family therapy day at West Oak Hospital. There are two letters from Houston to Mathers' one time partner, Terry, and one letter from David Wojnarowicz, written right after his controversial essay for a November 1990 Artists' Space show, "Witnesses: Against Our Vanishing," made headlines across the country. There is also one photo collage sent from Mathers, to Houston, in which Houston is pictured.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The collection was donated to NYU's Fales Library and Special Collections in 2015 and 2018 by William Ryder Mathers; the accession numbers associated with these gifts are 2015.433 and 2018.091.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact Fales Library and Special Collections, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596 with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Clippings (information artifacts); Correspondence.; Twelve-step programs; Drug addiction.; Collages (visual works); Artists and community -- United States; Substance abuse; Houston (Tex.) -- History.; Wojnarowicz, David
- [A.A. Step 1 Letter to William], c. 1989 (Box 1, Folder 1)
- [A.A.] Step 1 Monte Hewson, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 2)
- [A.A.] Step 2 Monte Hewson, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 3)
- Another "Timeless" Epissle from Montini [Letter], [undated] (Box 1, Folder 4)
- [Construction Paper Letter], July 9th 1989 (Box 1, Folder 5)
- Copy of Gateway to the Temple by Thubten Legshaw Gyatsho, circa 1980s (Box 1, Folder 23)
- Dearest Worm Farmer [Letter], August 1989 (Box 1, Folder 6)
- Dearest Wormus McDermus [Letter], August 29th 1989 (Box 1, Folder 7)
- Deer Dr. Vermicus MacDermicus [Letter], October 16th 1989 (Box 1, Folder 8)
- Dirge de Verm [Letter], December 1989 (Box 1, Folder 9)
- The Journals of Denton Welch Inscribed by Montanna Houston, 1985 (Box 3, Folder 1)
- [Letter from David Wojnarowicz], c. 1990 (Box 1, Folder 10)
- Letter from Montanna, circa 1982 (Box 1, Folder 22)
- Letter from Montanna to William Ryder Mathers, November 1989 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- [Letters to Terry from Montanna], 1982 (Box 1, Folder 11)
- [Misc. Correspondence and Collage], [undated] (Box 1, Folder 12)
- [Misc. Correspondence and Collage], [undated] (Box 1, Folder 13)
- [Misc. Letters to William Mathers], November 1989, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 14)
- Mont Belvieu [Letter], December 14th 1989 (Box 1, Folder 15)
- Negatives of Montanna at Apartment (New York City), 1979 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- Notes from the Asylum [Letter], August 21 1989 (Box 1, Folder 16)
- My Own Sexually Fixated Austin Collidge Yeerbook, [undated] (Box 1, Folder 17)
- Orphan Still Alive...[Letter], December 4 1989 (Box 1, Folder 18)
- There Was So Much Death [Letter], October 30 1989 (Box 1, Folder 19)
- [West Oaks Hospital Letter], August 24 1989 (Box 1, Folder 20)
- Wormicus Mathers [Letter], December 28 1989 (Box 1, Folder 21)
- OVERSIZE [William Mathers Photo Collage], [undated] (Box 2, Folder 1)